Henry B. Boynton Papers, 1931-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Henry B. Boynton Papers, 1931-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms92-002
2 boxes; 2.0 cu. ft.
This collection contains the papers of architect Henry B. Boynton. The bulk of the materials consists of financial and organizational material for the firm of Smithey & Boynton, and awards and honors bestowed on Boynton.
Henry B. Boynton
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Henry B. Boynton Papers were donated to Special Collections in January 1992.
Biographical Information
Henry B. Boynton was born in West Chicago, Illinois, in 1899 and grew up in Amelia County, Virginia. He graduated from Virginia Polytechnic Institute in 1921 with a B.S. in Agricultural Engineering and then again in 1923 with a B.S. in Civil Engineering. He then spent a year (1923-24) at the University of Illinois in Urbana taking architecture classes. He became a registered architect in Virginia in 1930 (he later registered in West Virginia, North Carolina, and Pennsylvania).
From 1924 to 1928, Boynton worked as a draftsman at Carneal & Johnston, Architects & Engineers, in Richmond, Virginia. In 1929 he worked as an associate with Louis Phillipe Smithey, Architect & Engineer, in Roanoke, Virginia. In 1935 he and Smithey became partners and formed Smithey & Boynton, Architects & Engineers, in Roanoke. Boynton became senior partner of the firm when Smithey retired in 1963.
Smithey & Boynton designed several structures over the years, including, in Roanoke, Christ Episcopal Church, the South Roanoke Fire Station, the Shenandoah Life Building, McClanaham Street Office Building, and the American Theater Building. The firm also designed Lane Stadium at Virginia Tech.
Associations with which Boynton was affiliated include the Virginia Chapter (later changed to the Virginia Society & Blue Ridge Chapter) of the American Institute of Architects from 1938 to his death. He served on the board of directors in 1952, 1953, and 1956, as vice-president in 1954, and president in 1955. He was a member of the State Registration Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, and Land Surveyors, as a Governor's appointee, from 1962-72 (President of the Board in 1967). He received a distinguished service award in 1980, and the Noland Award in 1989, both from the Virginia Society & Blue Ridge Chapter of the AIA.
Boynton served in the Army Corps of Engineers during WWII and completed his career as a colonel. He was a member of the Virginia Tech Alumni Board of Directors from 1969 to 1979 and Chair of its Annual Fund Committee from 1973 to 1979. He served on the Board of the VPI Educational Foundation, Inc., from 1978 to 1982. In 1976 Boynton recieved the Virginia Tech Alumni Distinguished Service.
Boynton died on September 13, 1991, at the age of 92, at his home in Roanoke.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of architect Henry B. Boynton. The bulk of the materials consists of financial and organizational material for the firm of Smithey & Boynton, and awards and honors bestowed on Boynton. The collection also includes a notebook from the Statics class he taught at VPI from 1931 to 1932.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Smithey & Boynton Records, 1922-1977. Ms92-027.
Separated Material
The following items were transferred from the Henry B. Boynton Papers to the Rare Book Collection (all bear Boynton's signature on the first free end paper):
Hedrick, Earle Raymond, Logarithmic and Trigonometric Tables (New York: Macmillan Company, 1918). QA531 .K4 1913 Small Spec
Hudson, Ralph G., The Engineers' Manual (New York: John Wiley & Sons, Inc., 1917). TA151 .H8 1917 Small Spec
MacCracken, H. N. and H. E. Sandison, Manual of Good English (New York: Macmillan Company, 1918). PE1408 .M23 1917 Small Spec
Wentworth, G. and D. E. Smith, Plane and Spherical Trigonometry (Boston: Ginn and Company, 1915). QA531 .W463 1915 Large Spec
Contents List
- "Statics course outline as given at VPI during the Spring quarter 1931-32 by H.B. Boynton," 1931-1932. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Cost accounting for Smithey & Boynton, 1935-1939. (Box-folder 1:2)
- General Smithey & Boynton Historical records, 1935-1982. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Cost accounting for Smithey & Boynton, 1940-1949. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Cost accounting for Smithey & Boynton, 1950-1954. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Cost accounting for Smithey & Boynton, 1955-1959. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Cost accounting for Smithey & Boynton, 1960-1964. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Report on Examination of Accounts and Financial Records for Smithey & Boynton, 1963. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Smithey & Boynton Partnership meeting minutes, 1963-1971. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Cost accounting for Smithey & Boynton, 1965-1969. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Atelier, Inc., 1969-1983. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Cost accounting for Smithey & Boynton, 1970-1972. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Review of accounting system and procedures for Smithey & Boynton, 1971. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Statement of Income for Smithey & Boynton, 1973. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Unaudited financial statements for Smithey & Boynton, 1974-1975. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Atelier building proposed expansion, 1976. (Box-folder 1:16)
- Unaudited financial statements for Smithey & Boynton, 1976-1977. (Box-folder 1:17)
- Unaudited financial statements for Smithey & Boynton, 1978-1979. (Box-folder 1:18)
- John M. Thompson's projects, 1979-1983. (Box-folder 1:19)
- Preparations for Boynton's retirement, 1980-1982. (Box-folder 1:20)
- Smithey & Boynton, P.C., Executive Committee minutes, 1980-1982. (Box-folder 1:21)
- Indemnification agreement/ownership transfer literature, 1980-1983. (Box-folder 1:22)
- Cash flow projections, 1981-1982. (Box-folder 1:23)
- Smithey & Boynton-Atelier agreement, 1982-1985. (Box-folder 1:24)
- Smithey & Boynton operating manual, 1983. (Box-folder 1:25)
- Noland award (clippings, program), awarded to Boynton, 1989. (Box-folder 1:26)
- Organization and function for Smithey & Boynton. (Box-folder 1:27)
- Resolution from the State Board for the Examination and Certification of Architects, Professional Engineers and Land Surveyors honoring Boynton for his work as a member and as President and Chairman of the Architectural Section of the Board, 1972. (Box-item 2:1)
- Certificate of Appreciation from the Virginia Foundation for Architectural Education, 1980. (Box-item 2:2)
- Distinguished Service Award of the Virginia Society of American Institute of Architects, 1980. (Box-item 2:3)
- Cross-stitch rendering of Smithey & Boynton logo ("Smithey & Boynton Architects & Engineers, 1928-1982"), [1982]. (Box-item 2:4)
- Collage of cut photographs of buildings that Boynton designed, with caption reading "With fondest recollections, Smithey & Boynton, 1928-1982." (Box-item 2:5)
- Resolution from Smithey & Boynton elevating Boynton to the position of Chairman Emeritus of the firm; signed by colleagues, coworkers, pupils and friends, 1983. (Box-item 2:6)
- Resolution by Planning Commission of the City of Roanoke commending the services of Boynton from 1960 to 1984, 1984. (Box-item 2:7)
- William C. Noland Award from the Virginia Society of the American Institute of Architects to Boynton, 1989. (Box-item 2:8)
- Resolution by the Architectural Review Board of Roanoke, Virginia, to recognize the meritorious service of Boynton, 1991. (Box-item 2:9)
- Seal press ("State of West Virginia, Architect, Henry B. Boynton, 392, Registered"). (Box-item 2:10)